welcome to Ife talks where we chat
openly with guest experts on their time
in the fitness industry and share some
tips on what we can all do to improve
[Music]
today's episode we've got Charlie and
for those who don't know we work
together at complete Fitness obviously
we've spent a bit of time around Fitness
before you're at Phoenix before you
moved over but for people who don't
recognize you already let people know a
little bit about what you're doing and
how you got there so how did I get there
stuck there so I actually started with
you which is quite cool because now I
technically work alongside you and they
were slightly different in our
businesses but
um yeah I must have been what 19 I
reckon 19 maybe 20 yeah and did a PT
course review
um really good uh getting qualified that
was fantastic then I started working
in my grandma's Garden oh yeah yeah yeah
I mean it was great memories but um
yeah just training people from my
Grandma's Garden we just felt like my
grandma's washing up and I've got like
people doing a group class or something
I don't like yeah that's my grandma I
mean it you know it worked and it's
where I started so I'm never gonna be
ashamed not only gonna be happy with
I've done that oh it sounds like she's
always been super supportive for you
though right oh yeah my grandma's like I
mean anyone who knows me
on a slight personal level they'll know
how much like um me and my grandma how
close we are
um really supportive of everything
um you know even when I've been failing
at a lot of things she's always been
there and pushed me in the right
direction so I'm always thankful for
that it's the same for my mum but um
started there then I moved into the
garage because it got dark and I was
thinking well it's pitch black here
who's going to turn up so with a little
bit of a light source a little heater
and I bought some more kit and then I
made the move to Phoenix which is really
good yeah
um it's just a stepping stone for me at
the time
um but that's probably where I started
to
meet some really good people help me
with my career yeah you had like Jack
and Rich and all the guys around yeah my
mate George as well it you know and then
I met Jordan there's a there's a couple
of other people as well but uh Jack was
definitely really influential I am
always grateful for that I mean it's
things like he gave me a bloody MacBook
yeah really I remember coming in and I
had a
HP Pavilion that my Grandad bought me in
2014 and it was like you turn it on it
was like a B-52 jet like everyone knew I
was in the stuff yeah and he basically
looked at me he goes that's disgusting
and I I was like yeah I understand
um and then like the next week he just
gave me oh that's good which is crazy
he's doing well for money so yeah yeah
no um so that was good
um so he was really interested about
influential not just by giving me an
extrinsic reward but he taught me a lot
in the sense of other things within
coaching and then one of my best mates
George hmm awesome yeah like just like
he's around my age as well not to say
Jack's really old but he's getting on
yeah
um no George has been really helpful as
well we start a similar time so it was
it was really handy having someone to
sort of go through that process with
Just Bounce the good and the bad often
then absolutely and another thing me and
George are kind of different but we work
really well together and it's like our
relationship as friends but he will give
me some of the best advice I've ever
received so again that really has helped
me and then yeah at Phoenix
loved it really did and then I went to
another gym which is the one I'm at now
which is complete Fitness where again
reunited with yourself yeah awesome as
well good gym isn't it oh yeah yeah I
always say that to people it's a bit of
a Hidden Gem because it's not super
duper busy all the time but it's really
well kitted out yeah and if you think
about it as well like it's a space and
like you said being hidden away I think
if you're a personal trainer and you're
fairly established I.E you're doing a
consistent amount of high sessions or it
could be lower at a higher rate
um where you have that consistency it's
a great place to go
um and then you know there's other steps
for the future but I'm obviously I'm
gonna speak for now but um yes perfect
isn't it that's what I say because when
the guys get like yourself when you get
towards the end of a level three you're
like yeah where's what gym do I go to
like what do I do next yeah and I do
always say like if you're starting out
and you're on zero to ten clients like
go find someone that's busy like doesn't
really make too much difference other
match as long as it's got some sort of a
fitness facility with lots of people
coming and going because you just
surround yourself with all the members
and you you learn the things that are
difficult to learn out of textbooks like
how to approach a client or a
prospective client yeah and like I said
you get around the other trainers there
and you can sort of see who's a few
years ahead of you doing the sort of
stuff that you want to do and you just
ask them how they got there or see if
you can Shadow or get some help to get
there I think it's good as as well if
you're in a busy gym like Phoenix is
really busy yeah you've got so many
different types of people coming through
the gym doors it's going to give you
more of an idea of maybe where you want
to sort of Branch yourself yeah yeah and
maybe not even just where you want to
you may like I never thought I'd be
working with
a lot of sort of older women let's say
I'm not saying it's older but like 40 to
60 and I've just ended up going a bit
more towards that direction because
that's like half of my 50 of my
clientele yeah
um and I never thought that would be the
case you know when I was doing the
course a long time ago I mean I thought
I'd be training like most young Lads
think when they get a PT you think
you're gonna be training the people
you're around people like me basically
yeah it doesn't work like that um you
might get a couple yeah and nothing
wrong with that but you know you're
there to help people with you know other
sort of problems that may have been a
dwelling problem for a long time and
they build the courage and they want to
be a client or someone they need
coaching so yeah that tends to be in the
later ages and 18 full of testosterone I
want to do bench press yeah yeah exactly
but have you noticed other than like the
types of clients you work with has there
been much of a difference between like
what you expected life as a PT to be
like compared to the reality of it oh
without a doubt I think
I'll start off with the reality I mean
I'll start off with what I thought so I
thought
I was going to get a permanent tan or
something far from that I mean I also
live in England so it's just raining all
the time it's great Skies also I'm not
going on the sun bears anytime soon I'm
supposed to be tanned I thought it's
just gonna be in chicken and broccoli
um all I could be talking about was
protein I was just gonna do upper body
and I thought everyone would gravitate
towards me yeah you should get paid to
work out better and you get paid to work
out like it you know and
um life doesn't work like that for a
starter
um also also that's very self-entitled
from myself assuming that people are
going to gravitate towards me just for
an appearance space and not what I'm
offering but that is what a lot of
people think initially is if I can get
myself in the best shape yeah people
will want to do the same thing as me but
how often do you see that as a mistake
so like um how do they experience
there's a lot of people they just see
one layer of like like the tip of an
iceberg and they assume that's the full
ticket for that individual for them to
to invest in so I.E you see some guy
with an eight pack but it's a picture
that's really filterized it's got like
changing the fillers
could be steroids or anything like that
and they're like that person is going to
help me specifically for my problem my
women at age 43 with two children
part-time cleaner and going through the
menopause at the start yeah they're not
gonna be able to relate it doesn't make
sense does it yeah um I think it and
it's not to say I mean you can have the
off sort of example but I think
experiences and things that you go away
and learn again it's judging a book by
its cover yeah and that can work in any
different way but um the reality go back
to your other question
well the reality is it's a fantastic job
in the sense that you learn so much from
the people you coach yeah
um
I think
I think every PC that's done it for
let's say longer than a year okay
because you know on the average is very
short turnover isn't that it's a high
turnover and I think if you've done it
for a year and you've really given it a
good go you realize how many hours you
have to put in yeah yeah I mean when you
start how many hours do you reckon you
put in I always say seven now it's
always like an apprenticeship so the
first year or two I might have been
doing like 40 to 60 hour weeks sometimes
and you it's not like you're getting
paid an hourly rate for those 40 to 60
hours either you're putting in loads of
time but you might barely be scraping
minimum wage back for the first part
when you're building it up I know I
remember when I told my mates I was like
this is what I charge per hour and uh
they're like that's like three times the
the minimum wage oh you must be racking
it in or whatever I'm like mate like I
sometimes will train a client then I
have to wait for like two hours and have
two more and then wait three and then
have two more and then if you look at
the community of how many hours you've
been in that gym yeah yes you can do
other bits and Bobs but it's not the
same it's not something you're clocking
at nine and you get that rate every
single hour from 9 until five and then
you go home it's like sometimes you got
sometimes the days work well and you can
schedule it right what you're saying
about that holidays are always quite
good yeah because you can group clients
together and you might be able to see
four or five people in five or six hours
yeah yeah in between but most of the
time you're gonna have people come in in
the mornings on my lunch breaks and
after work which then leaves you not
working at the time everyone else is at
work yeah you have to take that into
account and it's quite it can be quite
taxing but I think anyone it's not just
coaching I think any business that you
start no matter what especially for the
first two years is going to be taxing on
your mind your physical maybe spiritual
you know
um it's hard to switch off when it's
your business yeah you have to put a lot
of work in for in order to get yourself
up in that that ladder and then
eventually you'll find there's like a
comfortable level where you can sort of
withstain this but obviously we always
want to strive for more within reason
and then there's just Little Steps it's
it's the first two years I think is to
make a break for people and I think they
do say that any anyway yeah yeah yeah
because I think a lot of the times
people will come into it and it was when
I was at the gym group when I first
started there was a PT board it might
have been like between 10 or 15 of us at
any given time but you'd only see five
or six of us most of the time there and
then everyone else would sort of come
and go so if you want to be one of the
people who is working towards making
this map full-time yeah that first year
or two is the most important to get a
bit of a position it's a bit like it's a
bit like heartache for me in football I
look at some of my favorite football
teams and you see that some of the
players who stay there yeah for the
longest and you when you see the turtle
it just makes you a little bit emotional
but it is hard it's not and like I said
it's not just coaching it's any business
but you know you can maybe argue
coaching is a little bit harder than
other businesses because it's considered
as a luxury yeah which is a good debate
for that I'm sure we can talk forever
about the debate and you weighing it up
but um yeah the reality being it is not
just you have to work clothes it is a
really good job because you speak to
people I'm a sociable person yeah I've
never I mean
people who know me they know my GCC it's
not saying that defines me but yeah I
struggle to spell the word cat I mean
it's not it's not going well for me but
when it comes to speaking to people I
like to think I'm quite socially
intelligent oh definitely yeah um but I
can sit down a computer and be like I
could do plans now yeah which I never
thought would be good at because I never
did homework when I was at school and I
used to get a body kit for that but I
can do plans now but I I have a passion
for it now yeah so no it is is good and
then you know being your own boss as
well if you go to being self-employed
like
um yourself as well as me
you can be a bit more flexible even
though the funny thing is we'll just
work whatever hours anyway yeah but you
do have that that element where you can
say all right I'm going to take a bit of
time off you ain't got to go to your
boss and request your holiday from you a
lot of demand per year and then work
around everyone else I think you kind of
know where you stand as well because
and I'm not doing any comparison with
employ been employed by someone or being
self-employed but I don't feel like I
have to jump through certain levels of
different people in order to get
something I want I know if something
goes wrong it's my fault if something
goes well it's this might be your fault
yeah you know like this is and so I'm I
got my answer and I
I need to how I work with my brain I
need to know be quite straight up with
things yeah so be my boss working with a
business and I'm sure with yourself it
is nice because you know where you stand
and if you know where you stand you can
then picture where you're going to go
further yeah and just like training you
need to know what your goal is and then
you can make the little steps with that
and you can use that in business hence
why you have so many these mentors you
know and things like that which are not
massively cute but I don't know I'm more
self-taught sort of person it's like
anything it's like we're trainers to be
honest there's good mentors and bad
mentors and people say Better or Worse
yeah for you but I find like yeah on the
financial side of things I was one of
those books where Naval ravacan has got
a bit about
when you have paid a salary and you're
right right I get well two grand a month
you will spend up to about two grand
basically you might put something in the
savings and then you get a pay rise
you're like oh now I can spend a little
bit more so you're not you're not ever
really like able to put away or save
that much more compared to at least for
me going self-employed it's like right
I'll get paid lump sums when people pay
for sessions blocks months whatever it
be I find it easier track keeping a
track of all that and they're like right
so I know when this sort of money will
come in here and I'll put this aside
there and I'm I'm a lot more responsible
with my money than I ever have been
before I was self-employed oh definitely
I think that's a really good thing to
say actually because I don't think many
people talk about that
and I think
now like I was saying to you on the way
here I feel like I'm more of an adult
people beg to differ those people can
comment on that I will challenge you
okay but I feel like I have become more
of an adult recently especially in the
past couple years so when it comes to
managing your money I think if I did get
paid to fix Hillary knowing me I'd be
like well that's going on the night out
yeah that's going out with the boys and
that's going on I don't know like some
gaming or some gym clothes or something
I'm not actually really thinking of
anything that's going to be for
long-term helping me whether you put a
bit more money for your tax or that
could go towards a property or even like
food shop or something like yeah you
don't really some people do but I think
I I was glad I went into that
self-employed with me when I was quite
young I still am yeah
um because that has taught me to be a
bit more humble yeah yeah I mean I think
that's good you have to take the The
Good the good and the bad as well yeah
because it's not always the most stable
income but once you wrap your head
around it and find a way to make it work
for you like I said you're you're that
much more responsible when money does
come in not just to spunk on a night out
basically yeah I mean a good example is
when so I've for the past I'd say two
years I've been quite given my money
when you get paid I put x amount here
whatever when everyone got told on the
news we're going into the recession or
whatever I remember having a month where
everyone all my clients are like
obviously luxury or whatever they
stopped and then I like I had half of
what I'm used to earning but it was okay
because all the good maps I had I put
aside for in case that did happen yeah
um
and a bit better with my money the only
thing I'm bad with is bread sauce yeah
which is noticeable yeah it's easy to
just 10 15 pounds every time you go
right I know I know I mean I go I don't
know about you but I go through months
of being really organized in what I'm
eating my routine like it's hard to
sustain a really high level all the time
because we are only human yeah and other
factors have come in yeah take with my
clients I'm sure you've had clients
where they come in they're really ill
obviously their energy output the
recovery rate isn't going to be what
they're used to when they're not ill and
they get kind of this hand with it yeah
and obviously I can imagine yourself as
well as I we have to reassure him like
you're ill this is part of it yeah yeah
like it's fine it was important it's
like you know you're listening to your
body within a reason you know
um you've seen how you go so and that
momentum comes and goes whether it's
Food Training whatever people have
periods I was only chatting to one of
the ladies I was training this morning
saying hi
once you've trained for at least a year
maybe two and you get an idea for
busy times a year for you like socially
work-wise whatever you can start to
figure out right I know when the summer
comes round and barbecues come out and I
want to be a bit more social yeah that
might not be the time for me to try and
be as strict as possible on my diet yeah
it might be better to really hone in on
that when there are less socials other
times of the year so if you put that
hard work in earlier on in the year you
can afford to relax a little bit more
and you don't feel like you have to
restrict your social life when you've
got 10 calorie goals or whatever it
might be you need to hit that's why we
have like the term sun's out guns out or
like getting the Summer Body on or yeah
you know some girls say hot girls summer
you know yeah it's seasonal isn't it
yeah but
[Laughter]
um
yeah so I mean yeah I do with my clients
sometimes so like
some of my clients like if you looked at
maybe talk about calories okay so some
of them in the day before they train a
couple hours they want to eat something
so they don't have enough energy for
when they train with me and if they look
at the week
um then on Friday they're going to go
out for a few drinks so they calorie
Banks so they save a few more calories
that they can so when it comes to like
Friday night they don't feel like that
pressure yeah and you can do it also
then monthly and then the season will
like you know like you were saying so
even files right down to a day when
we're talking about sort of measuring it
but um
we could talk forever about calories
yeah but a bit like before we started
filming we were saying the best way to
do this with clients is rather than like
withhold that information from them and
be like I have all the answers you have
to pay me to have the answers like just
get in the bin yeah just teach people
how to like when you learn to drive the
whole goal should be this person has
come to you because they're not able to
be independent yeah in the gym but
they're coming to you to teach them to
be independent So eventually they get to
a point where they've learned everything
they need to learn and then they can go
on and continue this journey themselves
if they would like to whereas there are
some people who along that way they
learn to trust you because you have been
so honest with them and you have taught
them like right if you do this this will
happen yeah if you don't then that'll
happen yeah then that trust means they
do stick with you because goals might
change their situation might change they
know that you will be the honest person
to give them the answers that they can
then use going forward
I think as well like it depends where
your passion comes from like some people
are passionate but they're actually just
arrogant yeah yeah there's a lot of that
in Fitness oh yeah I mean that's what
the stereotype is it has changed over
definitely the past few years like
there's the classic stereotype of the
CrossFit have a ice bath then have a
coffee yeah yeah and then talk about
veganery or something I'm not saying
that's all you guys I'm not saying that
but there's a few
um but um
yeah I think you have to educate because
I think if you if my passion comes from
just I love sports okay and I've always
wanted to keep myself fit and active and
I've always grown up thinking the doctor
knows best you go to the doctor and you
feel ill and they always say you must
keep yourself active and do XYZ sort of
stuff my job is to keep accountability
and I just think look I think if we can
get more people feeling fitter and
better for themselves then the whole
nation slash world or whatever however
big you want to look at it it's just to
benefit from it yeah of course because
this is is clear you can see just on
data how good this sort of stuff is and
if you keep it closed away and you say
I'm the only individual that's going to
share that and then I mean it just shows
a lot about some people yeah yeah you're
gatekeeping aren't you that's all it is
and yeah it's a bit toxic yeah I'd say
it's a bit is toxic and you should want
to educate and that's why you can kind
of tell by people's posts like when I
have done posts on Instagram I've tried
to make an effort of just putting out
information there that I mean I might
get a client from it but my goal is Just
for information out there so someone can
look at that and think oh [\h__\h] I didn't
think of that or that's a really good
idea
um and then they start to implement that
into their lifestyle and that means you
know you're having a more positive
impact in another way yeah
um
yeah you should want to educate people
people come to you for a service for
them to get in a better place and I
don't probably wanna I don't want to
transfer my clients for 50 years if I
did it for that long you know you'd
worry like what what more is there to
teach me on a certain point right like
Fitness is as deep as you want to make
it but for the most part it is like I
said teaching some basic account
accountability yeah getting some sort of
structure in the gym and learning to
find a way to get consistency with like
food as well yeah but that shouldn't
take more than years and years really to
teach yeah we did talk about you're
going to have some clients
um that's purely on accountability yeah
in a sense they just need someone to say
look we're gonna be at the gym in there
um you're going to be there I'm going to
take you through your session I've done
the session you just do what I say
basically yeah that's fine I'm not
against that um because people are
honest with that you know the amount of
times I've had a couple clients I've
spoken to and say it's a kind of bull
sort of thing is and that's the main
goal with you sort of um hiring myself
and they go yeah I'll go that's fine
yeah you know but then I have other
clients who are like look I've got a
wedding in nine months I've been told if
I need to fit this dress size I need to
you know lose a couple inches there even
though we can't do the whole spot
reduction thing which everyone seems to
think that's you can just take a pill
and there you go you lose your gut do
some sits do some sit-ups and you've got
six packs
we'll get on to that in a second because
there's so many funny ones about that
but um they say look I've got nine
months so I have that as a scale you
know and then they're done and they're
sorted because that's what we need and
hopefully ideally in that nine months
they've learned enough for myself
providing I've done the service that I
say I do
um they've got all the information they
probably need to get to that goal yeah
and then they have a lovely wedding yeah
ideally no divorce yeah fingers crossed
guys but if you've been that person
who's been honest enough to help them in
the most ethical way you will be the
first person to pay Talent who should
barely need anything in the future right
yeah I think as well like you have so I
remember ages ago when you was my tutor
we're gonna need this bag now not to
like black and white TV there yes but
you know we're going back right and um
you were telling me people are more
you gave the example signed a really bad
back problem like spinal problem and
they and they acquired to you the people
respect you more if you're just honest
to say look I can't I'm gonna refer to
someone else because I don't have the
credentials to facilitate the goal that
you want to be achieved yeah and it's
the same with just being truthful people
will just be so much have more respect
for you yes it'll be the odd for you but
I'm looking at a majority here you know
there'll be a few people be annoyed but
like
being truthful was only going to be a
positive thing of course it is it's like
I mean because you'll get figured out if
you're not truthful like you might fool
someone once but it's only gonna be a
matter of time before they figure out
that you're talking out of your ass
basically oh yeah you get caught out
because they're going to ask you
questions eventually oh what is this and
you know you should everything that you
provide for your client in the sense of
in the gym outside gym advising anything
that your service provides you should be
100 really sure of what you're going to
be doing and you can back it up because
that's why you've implemented it in a
plan the session what you tell them
because it's meant to be directed for
them as an individual and then to
achieve the goals if it's a random
question for other things then yeah fair
enough as well yeah but yeah that's
that's why the hourly rate is what it is
because it's not that hour it's the time
you spend preparing for it beforehand
all the time you spent following up for
it afterwards but then like I said it I
never want to encourage any of the
people I've worked with before like
clients
um PT students whatever if a random
question comes up like for example if
someone wants to know something about a
ligament yeah nothing wrong with saying
like I don't know but I'll go find out
for you for next year that's so much
better than just making up your best
guess on the spot I've seen people do
that and stuff like that I think you
know I think when I very first started
PT I might have said a few things that
were like not exactly correct and that's
what I mean I'm honest about that yeah
but like I've been in this game not
massively long but I've definitely put
enough hours into the learn a lot more
oh cool because I my way is my
personality
like I've I've failed in so many
different things so I don't really I
don't let that stop me I'm willing to I
want to learn as much as I can so I can
provide the best service and help for
people yeah but you know we all say
sometimes a little bit controversial
things you know it doesn't even have to
be in Fitness you know oh there's so
much stuff I would look back on when I
first started out but I'd never do that
again I've got I've got a funny story so
how's that uh Phoenix uh so you got rich
there you've got Jack you've got George
we had a few other people in there
I wrote a plan out and
I'm not I'm not blaming dyslexia because
there's nothing to do just be dyslexic
but my terminology for all exercises
like it's disgustingly bad and you you
have to try and work out for a good five
minutes why I've given that a word for
an exercise that makes no sense there's
no correlation right and I gave we were
doing like an Imam and at the end I call
them hois but basically you just pick up
a medicine ball and you put it over yeah
and I had like eight PT's just shouting
at me saying I'm thick which is true to
a certain degree when it comes to that
and that was heartbreaking so but at the
end of the day the stuff that you're
applying regardless of what you call it
it's still getting the result you want
to get oh I literally no I um I'm a
little bit stubborn I still call it
always just to piss them off because I'm
not let well I had to change a lot but
yeah don't worry about that the holes
are still in there which Jack will kill
me for he'll like really have a go at me
but it makes sense because you had to go
yeah
but um for clients though if that sticks
and they remember what that exercise is
yeah it's way better than giving them
the long-term analogy of saying oh and
this is a contralateral that's why Z
like that can get in the bin yeah yeah
and the terminology is good if you're
gonna go talk to that person's physio
yeah but if you're just talking to your
client and you want them to remember all
the exercises so they can do it by
themselves pull it wherever you want
mate I'm starting to March mate I'm
getting more people to say holy now just
because I'm going to take it as far as
we can I know it's worldwide you know
whatever if there's a lot of people in
gyms just saying oh we'll say I was Ahoy
you know where it started from Norwich
is me so the dyslexic 24 year old
Norwich so not great but honestly I
think that's one of the best things you
do is you can make that hour enjoyable
for your clients like just finding a way
for someone who's otherwise going to
feel chances are probably quite
intimidated by the gym not sure of what
to do or the classic ones everyone's
worried but everyone else is looking at
them so how you can find a way to just
be like welcome and make someone feel at
home and comfortable yeah that is worth
way more than knowing the difference
between all your cruciate ligaments oh
oh it definitely is and that goes down
to people management yeah like I've
worked with
I mean I reckon most clients have had
they've all struggled with some sort of
mental health sort of uh situation
varying from like uh severe depression
or maybe just gym anxiety or social
anxiety
Etc so the worst thing you can do is
come in tell them a load of random words
are in Latin yeah that are crazy and
then tell me a load of facts that if you
don't get yourself sorted this is what's
gonna happen which is very subjective by
the way yeah
um yeah so it's all about making a
positive environment and I always say if
I have anyone new I said the main goal
first is me making sure you guys feel
comfortable yeah yeah I think because if
you can get if people can feel
comfortable they can feel focused in the
head and then they can really take on
board what you're saying and if they've
got too much of a of a sort of um the
panicking or worrying about what others
think what you tell them is probably not
sinking in and they're just gonna have a
horrible time in an environment they're
not really enjoy and it's just going to
feel horrible for them and you want them
to enjoy their Fitness that's why
like I don't get me wrong I have
opinions about different styles of
training but if it works for some people
and it becomes sustainable and
consistent I have no problem with that
and you know that's how honest I am with
it all so yeah the goal is to make him
feel good yeah okay so and they feel
comfortable in whatever environment not
telling them you know you you'll die at
the age of 34 if you don't do an
overhead press I mean yeah or don't do
burpees before bed or whatever it is but
you can but you can always scale it from
there once they're having fun and
enjoying the gym you can start to layer
it up a little bit but you don't need to
come in on day one of your vastus
medialis and this is your Lateralus and
this is that and this is that I mean
that's just they don't they don't want
no care about stuff like that they just
want the result at the end of the day
yeah that's some real boring stuff half
the time
no one will come in and be like oh
that's a nice part you need like no give
a [\h__\h] yeah no one cares about that yeah
that's what I always say because when
you have to learn the anatomy part of
the course is like you need to know this
if you're again going to talk to other
professionals but yeah your job isn't to
regurgitate this to clients because they
don't care you need to take the complex
stuff and make it simple and easy to
understand you are the go-between
between between the complex terminology
and what the client's going to remember
for the next session or when they're
explaining it to their friends yeah I
think um
I mean I'm sure you can easily have an
opinion on this but I think it's for
each client is so individual and each
client you have to think there's a
certain way of how you coach them in the
sense of the vocabulary you use yeah
the body language the conversations yeah
and how you're going to get the best out
of them you have it's like a lot of
people that's why I'm not the biggest
fan of generic plans yes it may work for
some people but that may be like five
percent that might be five people at 100
yeah yeah so it's just like I bet
they'll show the best results be like
this can work for everyone it doesn't
work it doesn't work like that from a
start yeah it's just a masses and masses
of people it hasn't worked for but you
don't talk about yeah exactly so you
must have some clients where you have to
almost change like you have your your
ethos and you have the way you coach and
your values and this is how I conduct
myself but you can always slightly
change it a little bit because you know
how to get the best out of that
individual yeah yeah you've got your
principles and stuff with Progressive
overloads calorie Surplus restriction
whatever it might be but yeah it's got
to be tailored to that person I say even
down to the type of vocabulary that you
use like some clients you can be really
comfortable with and you can swear
around them and be quite casual oh yeah
I do yeah yeah and then other times you
have people come in and it is a bit more
proper and you do need to be a bit more
professional but it is very individual
on that person that you've got in front
of you there and then yeah definitely
um and after after a month you kind of
work out exactly where that client is
some take longer some take quicker you
know some people are really open about
whatever yeah but um
yeah it's definitely some things I'll
say around other clients uh
uh like sort of jokes and things like
that some probably don't but that's
that's not a problem because you know
I'm also only human as well yeah but
like you said both people are still
there to have a good time it's a bit
like when I train Pete like he's always
dead Keen he's there for the exercise
just as much looks forward to coming and
chatting to you about the football as he
does anything that's why he's a good lad
I mean Arsenal yeah you know you did
well yeah yeah they won't quite City
yeah but you know yeah so up City
basically but yeah if you can make the
people feel comfortable then they'll
just they'll enjoy the process and that
consistency will come that way rather
than trying to be like this is the most
scientifically proven method yeah the
best results because if they don't like
it they won't stick to it yeah if you
like something you're more motivated to
do something yeah yeah exactly if I
don't like someone I'm probably not
going to do it for my list like that's
just me being honest and I think that's
me being honest with the whole world
because that's what the world really
thinks yeah no you know like I don't
make everyone have to do a certain
exercise if they really don't like it
then there are subjects issues I'm
qualified enough and we've got enough
experience for me to find different
variants of different movements that's
part of your job and if they don't like
doing bench press then there's many
other things I mean necessarily more
horizontal presses you could you could
you know horizontal pushes you could put
in there so but you run into people like
no we need to do bench press because it
does this and that that's but that is
the problem with the coaching themselves
because like I said go back to the
arrogance thing they're like oh you
questioned me I'm going to make you do
anyway and then they make up some random
reason and say why I'm right yeah and
it's one-way communication rather than
working as a team to reduce oh you're
boring don't do that again yeah I mean
they do do it again but it's it's quite
bad like that but I'm trying to think of
other things as well but they that's the
thing you whether the PT learns or not
from it those clients even come back of
it don't basically and if you find that
I find the most important metric for
myself and most pts when they get
started is their retention rate and how
often they have clients come back or
drop out within the first few weeks
basically if you've got
there might be loads of people who come
and have like a really high churn right
churn rate they might throw in a load of
effort on their marketing and their
social media presence and they get 50
new clients sign up every month yeah but
45 of those drop out within a week then
like you're just spinning your wheels
for nothing it's too much stress as well
yeah like I wouldn't want to have it I
wouldn't want to live a lot it's just it
can be a stressful job anyway because
you're running your own business so your
own boss right but I wouldn't want to go
under that way of running my business
you know retention rate is really
important and also like consistency as
well yeah like
you want results and not the reasons for
it results because it shows that you're
a good coach and you can do your job and
you can do your job and then you can
actually I would rather have a project
to work with and get to that result than
a half-ass like a build will be I'm
sorry if I paid for a building he did 20
the job yeah he can get yeah
no of course you're not no you're not so
you obviously but it is the relationship
between yourself and the client
sometimes people are showing you a
couple times they're like maybe not you
know I'm not everyone's cup of tea
personality is a big thing like we were
saying we're marching last time he was
here like you need to be able to get on
with someone at a base level if you're
going to spend between what
realistically one to three four hours a
week with them yeah um if you if you
don't click and that hour feels like two
three hours then no matter how good the
training is they're probably gonna go
with someone they get on with a little
bit better yeah I mean I don't know
about you but I've never I know some pts
who get really upset when a next client
goes to someone else I'm not I don't not
really like that because I only I work
with what I've got in front of me yeah
and if you're not under my team that's
fine not a problem always welcome back
you know within you know if I can fit
you in obviously yeah but I've never had
a problem with someone going with
someone else and I would like it for
another reason yeah because at the day
you know I just because you had to go I
must try and Achieve like oh if someone
else is going to do that for you then
you're more than welcome to go try you
know like yeah you don't own these
people just because they wanted to like
I know you learn how to train with you
basically yeah it's yeah we don't own
them so and
this is another thing that we can talk
about is that some people like sometimes
can be too scared to leave yeah like
coaches you know like real drill
sergeants and you must do this and like
it's not me it's not my personality yeah
there's different personalities in this
game
I mean we can go for all the
personalities you've got the drill
sergeants yeah you've got the really
laid-back guys they get all spiritual
about coffee yeah we got like say the
narcissist who come in and it's all
about them and oh God they're physique
and what they've done and how you should
do exactly what they do they're painful
to watch they really are yeah um that
hurts yeah
um and you saw the normal people who
like sports and they're like Fitness
just kind of the route they've always
known in their whole life when they were
younger yeah I feel like that's sort of
our sort of vibe of that yeah
um and they're like the really the main
ones
um maybe or just the really sociable
ones again like you can dip in a little
bit maybe a big graph like a massive
Venn diagram or something you have a bit
of everything but um it's quite
interesting the PT world I think it's
interesting because when you run your
own business it's up to you whatever you
do yeah yeah some people open-ended
isn't it you could do whatever I mean I
in my last when I was working at Phoenix
um lovely guy but his Niche was
technically being a knight like dressing
up in armor yeah I mean I'm I'm over
there doing full body workout and then
you got in the other room like someone
jousting or something throwing axis I
mean that's a very Niche thing just
saying that doesn't happen everywhere
maybe it's just Norwich but yeah
and then you've got people who just do
like fighting and like MMA boxing that's
fine as well yeah and then um people
just want to do yoga you know the
industry is and but they take all
different ways down different routes
yeah they want to tailor it to their
personality yeah yeah but yeah do you
say it's gone kind of to plan in terms
of where you expected yourself to go
with the industry
um basing off what when I was younger
like when I got qualified yeah yeah like
when you got into it when you saw
because you know what you're a few years
into this now and since you're yeah I'm
technically three but yeah I always
based off when I started at Phoenix
because in my grandma's Garden next to a
lavender Bush yeah it's not really the
same is it you're still learning you're
still working on your trade but I know
I'm learning it is we're doing a legs
bums tunnels for free women in my
grandma's Garden yeah true yeah that's
uh weird days but you know I don't
regret them but um yeah where I think
what am I happy where it's gone yeah
yeah definitely definitely because I
didn't think I'd be self-employed
so early into it yeah but I'm not going
to be harsh myself I did like and I'm
not very
good to give myself self praise anyway
like the self-reflection thing in a
positive way but
I am like proud of myself that I did put
a lot of work in so I didn't think I had
the work ethic and clearly I've shown
that now
um to go self-employed already
um it's taught me a lot of things as
like as a hit on based on a human level
and just maturing a little bit more
um yeah I'm really happy where it's gone
like I've got every single one of my
clients I'm so excited to see
I work in a gym that's really good yeah
it's perfect for me as an individual
yeah and yeah I just have fun with it
I'm not really regretting any day I go
to work I've never had that I don't
think I've had a single day where i'm
like I wish I did something else yeah I
wish I did something else I'm actually
I'm really content I'm really happy with
where I am right now obviously I'm
always wanting to strive for more like
everyone should even if it's by little
marginal things you know yeah
um
but that's part of the game that's
running a business yeah you've got to be
working towards something else otherwise
you stagnate and then the next hungrier
person over there and to be fair like
talking about like a competitive level I
never really worried too much about what
other people do just only myself yeah
like that is one thing I'm good I'm good
at looking at my old self thinking okay
well that was better you know whether it
be with money whether it be with how I
come across to people whether it be my
body language whether it be
how I dress to work I mean I got when I
was working at Phoenix again jack he's
not a bully he's very helpful but and
George they brutalized some of the
things I wore to work yeah and I'm glad
they did because it helped me in other
aspects in life yeah socialize and go
nights out yeah but my dress sense was a
little bit
I don't know I felt like I was a little
bit homeless at times it was I mean the
colors weren't right either we're
talking luminous green shoes with dark
navy blue Adidas sort of trekkies and
then maybe like a pink top it was
worrying yeah but I've changed that now
so I'm happy I've improved on that but
yeah as an overall I'm really happy
where it's gone good and it's only going
to get better yeah well you seem to get
more and more professional and Slick
every single time like yeah before you
came over to complete I'd seen you work
with clients yeah yeah what's he gonna
be like yeah
and I knew you were doing a good job
over at Phoenix from like the stuff I
saw yeah yeah then actually seeing the
way you work with clients it's been good
to see how far you've come on so it's
like when you first came onto a level
two and stuff yeah I think I think the
key to that was to not think you're
better than everyone else yeah
understand that anyone can teach you
anything yeah so like the whole they do
that whole comparison like the example
of you know the cleaner can teach you
some something as well as the CEO and
giving each other the same amount of
respect and I've always looked at it
like that
um because I don't really have many
qualifications to my name and I had to
work almost from the bottom so to be
where I'm at even though it's not the
top it's a hell of a lot better yeah
it's a step up and at one point I never
thought I'd be where I am now I
generally thought like I'd be doing the
same job like I used to clean this cat
it was it was careful it's now abandoned
times but I used to clean that gym and I
used to be in my bloody
like footy shorts with a top off clean
and sauna at like 10 p.m and then I had
the cycle back into the city it was like
12 miles every day and it was like seven
days a week yeah and I and that was me
cleaning the gym and then I got
qualified as a PT then I had to go in my
grandma's Garden get clients and then I
went to Phoenix and now I'm here so I
was it was only a dream when I was a
cleaner to be where I am now so I'm I'm
very thankful for that but you have to
remember those things yeah of course
because if you don't then you just
you're just gonna you're never going to
be sort of content or happy you know
yeah and that's that's an important
thing because there is more to life than
work yes it does pay the bills yeah and
that is an essential because that's how
it works but you got to be happy yeah
and we were saying earlier about like
the work wallet is great and while I
find my days go so quickly like I never
feel like I'm watching with clients so
when you finish a long day it's like I
feel like I've been in the gym five
minutes and I've been there eight hours
yeah but you've also got to recognize
the toll that takes on you and the time
you need to recover and recharge to then
be able to provide that service again
for someone they think you just train
all the time I mean I don't I I lift
weights for people I listen to some
people's sort of problems I give my best
advice as I can I talk about funny stuff
that I've done or they've done or
whatever like yeah it's like there's a
talking a lot as well I mean one day I
booked in eight people back to back I'm
never doing that again everyone's made
that mistake once I was I was amazed
especially broken I didn't know who I
was I felt 48 I had gray hairs my
hairline was going further back than
anything yeah I was scared I didn't feel
great after so yeah don't book eight
back-to-backs just constant talking for
eight hours yeah and that first hour has
to be the same as the last one of course
yeah so because otherwise your car is
going to think who's this mom who's just
walked in telling me to do yeah that
pull down like yeah like a zombie but
I've done a similar thing you have those
long days back-to-back clients no breaks
yeah I got home I was like I just want
to lay in bed Turn All the Lights Off
just get in the fetal position yeah just
not talk to anyone for a day but yeah
yeah I mean
I feel bad sometimes you know obviously
different my mum at the moment I get
home for a long day at work and
sometimes my social work is gone and my
mum's lovely and sometimes you know
she'll be making tea from a step down
and she'll say how your day is I just
look at her like I've just died inside
and she's like okay he's had a long day
yeah yeah not great
um but no I still love it you know it's
just sometimes it can take a toll on you
so you do have to be wary like I don't
work on the weekends I do a little bit
of like I say paperwork I've got my
laptop check through people's plans what
they've done message clients on WhatsApp
but as my weekend goes there's a normal
weekend for anyone else as it should
you've got to set those boundaries
haven't you because yeah I had that
problem once where there was a period
where I worked every other weekend so
one week I'd go Monday through to Sunday
I'd work every single day and then I'd
only get every other Saturday off that's
right and that killed me like I was at
the time I think towards the start of it
was when I was still at my parents and
they come I'm like you're a miserable
bastard yeah and they just didn't they
didn't get it when Paris then qualified
and she went through a similar type of
thing oh it's just like you've got to
set some boundaries here yeah
early 20s oh you're early 20s as well
good you'll be full alive you're gonna
love it there's me I literally dive
about caffeine yeah otherwise I've got
an ivy in a can you leave me I'm in
hospital bed because I'm just like dying
there just because I'm a knackered yeah
you're saying earlier about people
you've learned a lot from like Jack Rich
George and all that through Phoenix have
you found many other people that you've
learned from sort of not necessarily
inside Fitness but outside of like the
business and that side of things
[Music]
um
um I would say definitely uh Jordan
Peterson yeah I know there's going to be
people who like there'll be some
comments outside my house with torches
like no I mean I was you know I mean you
I was quite open with sort of like my
amount of Health with you
um
and when I was like when I was living
with my grandma like during covid like
it was the most demotivated I've ever
been and I almost felt like I couldn't
turn any direction and a lot of people
took what he said out of context but
just making your bed yeah almost like
they made out he's been condescending or
patronizing but I made my bed I actually
felt a little bit better because I felt
I was so useless and deep motivated that
I couldn't do something like that and
when I did it in my head I don't know
what chemical it is but I just thought
oh nice cool and that kind of made me
think well if I could do that maybe I
can wake up just a little bit earlier
even half an hour yeah I did that and
then I said well I need to exercise
really why don't I just go for a jog for
20 minutes around the block I did that
and then it was all stepping stones for
me to and that I'm not saying it was a
soul starting point for me but it's
taking that first box isn't it and I use
that with my clients now and that's how
they've progressed as well and it's only
a positive thing there's no like he does
not get anything from that exactly yeah
you might buy his book you might give
him a tenor or something but yeah but
you know I mean is actually it was
really valuable so I look at people like
him obviously my grandma without a doubt
and she has very uh like values and
things like that it's always just think
how can she have a more of a positive
impact
um and she's obviously someone that's
helped me a lot and then um
yeah I mean there's not really too many
people I'm not really one to watch lots
of TV I watch bits of YouTube and things
like that I could argue set an athletes
you know that I like but I don't really
they never really feels more of a
personal level in comparison to what
Jordan Peterson said I'm not going off
that one example there's many examples
I'm going to make that clear yeah
um
and that that aligned well with me I
mean there's other people as well but I
think he was the main person that stood
out might be because he's popular at
that point at his Peak or whatever but
uh his peer views on just helping
um young people I know a specific young
member is women as well yeah of course
um just to feel better
uh really did help so I use that
probably as an example yeah and maybe
you feel better expired to be yeah yeah
I think a lot of people are so ready
like I said to get the Torches out and
try and burn people to understand about
a certain comment or a statement it's
like yeah when you are someone like that
and it's your job to speak publicly
you're going to speak a lot and
sometimes not everything's going to
resonate with everyone and that's okay
like you can let that be of value to
someone else just because it doesn't
necessarily work towards what you're
trying to do it might work for someone
else and that that's fine you don't need
to burn the thing down I totally
understand and there's no perfect world
there's no perfect person I'm I'm not
perfect and you're not perfect no one is
actually perfect like yeah people make
out like they paint this Utopia of a
world it's actually it's unsaturated
it's done un artificial artificial like
it's not it's not actually real yes say
that no one's done nothing wrong of
course we have yeah you know and um I
mean I can go in a whole another
conversation alone but yeah of course
when you put the Limelight it's the same
with Fitness when you put a comment out
there people are going to be like oh I
don't agree with that or something like
that yeah and that's why I'm very
specific in what I say because I want
people to be clear in what it is not
because it's over the fact someone might
argue me I have no Pro I could debate
all day
um but if it's only a positive thing
that's only have a positive impact you
shouldn't really have too many comments
on that saying exactly yeah people will
find a way yeah yeah you're really good
rich is also really good at it in terms
of being really clear about who he's
talking to and how he's trying to help
that person and if that's not you that's
fine you just move on someone else who
is trying to help you in your specific
way of doing things yeah I know I mean
like he puts a lot of stuff so he's in
more of a firing line than I would be in
the sense of comments and you know I see
comments and sometimes his stuff 90 of
it's positive yeah I want to make that
clear but like 10 you get the random
person who just wants to say something
that's really irrelevant and half the
time if I'm honest it's people who are
not open-minded
um they may they may not I'm not saying
you have to be qualified to give advice
I think experience is what oh shows yeah
a qualification sure does show that you
know something yeah it'll get everyone
to like the same standard so to speak
but then beyond that there's such a wide
spectrum what's It Rich has lots of
qualifications and he's very experienced
and yeah he's been in the game for a bit
of time so when they argue I'm just like
stop picking the wrong fight here yeah
picking the wrong fight here but some
people just want to get a thrill out of
it they get a bit of sort of adrenaline
from having an argument and
I don't I don't really get it yeah that
is just how the world is so I'm not
gonna I'm not gonna cry about it for
about hours and hours and on because
that's just how it is you know yeah
there'll be some things about me some
people don't like there'll be some
things about me people love you know and
that's probably the beauty of it that's
that's what I see is a perfect thing not
this whole
on an artificial thing always absolutely
everything was nothing wrong with it
like well you know so yeah I'm not
afraid to really say like I draw pizza
and help me he did yeah it was only a
positive thing he never said anything
controversial that I agreed with yeah
and that's what I'm basing that off yeah
you know a lot of people they want to
jump to a conclusion say this is because
he said this one thing I'm going to hate
him straight away and I think that's
really unprogressive it's regressive
because you're not being you can't have
a conversation and you should be able to
have a conversation and I've met loads
of people already and I'm only 24 but
obviously I speak to a lot of people I
disagree with me I've never had that
have a soul intake in the sense that I'm
always now going to think negatively on
them no never held on to that I don't
want to hold grudges so you know it's
things like it's like rejection right
like you should have to learn to deal
with this as a part of life yeah but
I'll be rejected more than any sort of
bad transfer in a window mate it was
yeah but I'm not gonna hold a grudge on
anyone because Everyone's entitled to
their own opinion I'm not gonna hate on
anyone I don't think there's a
reasonable thing to do yeah and I
understand there's lots of opportunity
out there so why would you not just keep
going exactly like even the best teams
in the league don't go undefeated every
single year like you're still gonna have
to learn to take your loss be humble
about it and just move on and still do
what you want to do absolutely and this
links to probably like mental health and
like obviously there was a mental health
qualification Etc
um insecurities yeah yeah I'm gonna be
honest like when I was probably I reckon
in between the ages of
like I I think I truly believe in myself
and I think a lot of people who know me
closer I have changed a lot in the past
couple of years that means though from
the ages I reckon from 17 to 22 I was a
little bit I was you know I just had a
little traits of me that weren't the
most you know because it can be a little
bit toxic because I was a little bit
insecure in other things you know yeah
um and I've dealt with them now I've
just open up and speaking about people
yeah because I had my fair share of sort
of slight problems like a lot of people
do yeah
um so insecurity can be a big thing yeah
people don't know how to really accept
it and their perception changes yeah
sometimes they're insecure it's probably
not something to be even insecure about
especially in Fitness you find the
people who from the outside looking in
you might be like they're set they've
got it all going on you start talking to
them and they've got little things but
they're self-conscious or insecure about
or they have certain fears of failing at
something or another like it's about how
you sort of deal with it and try and
work around slash overcome these things
without letting it entirely consume you
basically what I find really interested
in is if you ever go to a 24-hour gym
and you go in the lay of hours I'm so
I'm talking like sorry 8 30 p.m onwards
you'll be surprised to see
as many members lots of women as well
who go there train on their own and they
have their own they've had a level of
hardship where they've had to deal with
a lot of stuff yeah and it's I don't
it's happened any time but I'm just
saying particularly this time when I've
had conversations with people they've
had to go through really dark
you know places and a lot of things to
you know conquer and get through and
leap barriers it's quite interesting and
they're very hard on themselves yeah
they still keep going and that's very
it's actually quite admiring because you
think when you've got all this sort of
setbacks and you still keep going that's
what's that's great to see and that's
really inspiring and I think that's not
really talked about a lot now and then
it is you'll get a video come up on
Instagram or social media of like an
extreme weight loss or something someone
who started out let's say you know 130
kilos and they went all the way down to
90 or something like it's incredible
achievement and they've had to go
through lots of barriers but um when you
people who train quite late I've noticed
yeah they they have their own little
sort of archery they've got through yeah
definitely yeah I think like you said
earlier if you try and pretend that
you're perfect and you've not got
anything that you're working on No One's
Gonna
relate to that or feel like oh well I I
don't feel any better for that because
he is saying he's perfect and he doesn't
have any problems where if you can own
I'm going through some [\h__\h] right now
but I'm still I'm going through it and
you can find ways around it that will or
potentially Inspire that person to be ah
I have got some [\h__\h] going on but like
you there is a light at the end of a
tunnel and you can persevere because
I've seen this person do it I've seen
that person do this yeah I mean it was a
about a year ago I had a proper deep
chat with my grandma just talking about
like not an arrogant way myself and she
said one good thing about me sounds like
there's not many but could could be we
don't know so it's all opinion based
yeah but she said one good thing about
me is I know who I am and I know what I
want yeah and I only discovered that
recently and when you know that you've
got a bit more of a focus and more you
can see that light a bit more it's a bit
brighter so you know kind of where
you're going than being in the black
room not knowing where to go because you
don't know who yourself is you don't
know your character and it takes time
experiences is what can be a catalyst
for you to find that light yeah okay but
a lot of people who do struggle from the
experiences I've had with
conversations with many people I've
worked with in the various jobs I've
done already
is that
if they struggle to find out who they
are and what they want and they sort of
succumb to the modern day Society of
what it is the expectations of what it
is to be great or in this face or doing
well then they
um anxieties and depression all these
things sort of slowly creep in or you
get little bits of it and I think that's
why it's really important to maybe
self-reflect as much as you can and
really sort of I actually have a
personal diary so yeah I write down
things like you have white balls or your
personal diet I write down things that
about myself and I I can be quite
critical but in in a constructive way
yeah and that makes me kind of realize
who I am and I have a lot of ownership
like if I've ever
if you look at relationship I've ever
done that like a mistake or there's no
one else other than me and that's made
me be better than just looking at
excuses and hiding away from it and
making this problem seep even deeper so
I think it is really important to know
yourself and know what you want because
then you're a bit more grounded and you
have more of an idea exactly where you
should go yeah and if you have that it
does in my experience the people I've
spoken to it has less probability of the
depression depression and anxiety
creeping in yeah we just only have a
better quality of life for yourself and
we want everyone to you know feel better
don't we I mean well I like to think so
yeah yeah you know
so that's that's the thing yeah it's
like when you said about being
self-employed like things are going
right great that's my fault but if
things aren't going to right that's my
fault too so I need to work on that but
it's for people who are self-employed it
is so so important to have those people
around you because it's great if you can
be introspective and looking internally
about right this is what I'm good at
this is what I can work on but yeah it's
a difficult skill to develop and what's
easier sometimes is if you have a close
circle of people around you where you
can be open and honest about things like
certain things people don't want to
always talk about like mental health
things people are working through or
even finances and stuff as a PT not
everyone wants to talk about it's a bit
of a taboo in terms of how much money do
you earn but I only need at least one or
two people to talk to and be like right
I made this much this month I need to do
that to make sure I'm here because
otherwise like if you leave that all on
yourself
heavy weight to Bear after all it is and
like this one I think to myself a lot
and I do talk to myself a lot you know
it's funny anyway who has the time the
stuff I say but
um sometimes it can be overwhelming and
I think so if we was to use the lockdown
as an example I think I can speak for a
lot of people because we were isolated
you can see the effects of people just
thinking continuously on their own and
how it can be quite problematic yeah
yeah because you haven't really got many
people to turn to
um and there's loads of different
fundamentals in that for me I remember
Jack saying it was like a make a break
for some people and you can look in a
business
um point of view or you can look at it
as a your own character for me I
remember I just I was my heaviest ever
been I think I was like 83 84 kilos and
I was the weakest I had ever been so I
was very like and you can see a
comparison picture of my my Instagram
and I just did not feel great at all and
then I had a realization I was thinking
to myself I really thought right I need
to change something and then that's when
it happened when I had something like
Jordan Peterson said and my grandma
helping me it was a multitude of
different things and as an overall uh
conclusion set me in a better and more
correct direction yeah I look at it so
that's probably one of my lowest points
if not my lowest and everything since
then has only been upwards so that's a
really good way to look at it and I'm
sure there's a lot of people who do
share that um but lockdown was not just
in our industry in every industry but
especially just our industry I think
it's because it's Fitness everyone had
their backs against the wall really when
the gyms closed and everything oh yeah
yeah it was make or break for so so many
people and I noticed
more so personally and mentally like I
always I always knew I was introverted
I'd always sort of pigeonholed myself
but I'm fine all by myself you know I'm
yeah I'd much rather spend time by
myself I don't I like being around
people but it does take its toll and it
does drain the social battery a bit Yeah
but it was only when I didn't really
have anyone else around or very very
limited social capacity I was like [\h__\h]
I do still need some level of social
interaction otherwise I'm going to go
completely crazy here and you you do
figure out how much is like it's a bit
like when you when you train and Mike
Israel talks a little bit about training
landmarks and you've got your minimum
effective volume so like the least
amount of work you can do in the gym to
provide a response and an improvement
and you've got your maximum recoverable
volume so the other end of that is the
most you can do in the gym before you
start burning out and breaking down
rather than growing and repairing
there's definitely a social and an
emotional aspect of that as well where
everyone must have like a minimum amount
of social interaction a feeling of like
being a part of a community and XYZ yeah
but then there's also a top end of that
and you've got to see where you fall on
that because there'll be certain days
weeks months where you are maxed out
whether you're seeing clients out with
friends whatever and you need to make
sure you're looking after yourself and
getting that time to like write your
diary do your stuff that you know was
gonna keep you moving forwards but then
also when things are quieter is making
sure you reach out to talk to your
friends yeah or go to that social event
when you might rather just want to lay
in bed play games really work and just
be by yourself like yeah I think it's um
the pressure you so like you'll have it
when you're running a business you're
probably there is probably I reckon like
20 things you need to do we say you need
to do you can you can do right yeah but
you only probably do a couple you know
within a week or something like that but
if you look at the 20s I must do this
like do one thing at a time and then you
work onto the next thing
um it's like when you look at tests you
know oh 50 questions oh [\h__\h] [\h__\h] that I
ain't gonna do this yeah you can just do
one question at a time yeah you know
it's like when people look at their they
say we use weight loss as an example we
go so we're looking to lose maybe 20
kilos well we're actually going to just
look at five each time yeah or even one
kilo per day just get that first one
then get two yeah and then I work it
like that and a lot of people don't
always think like that and it's nice to
have someone else to talk to about
things like that to reassure
um because it's easy to get overwhelmed
it's so easy and I you know I still do
it to this day but I'm a lot better at
handling it it's my coping mechanism now
is I said I've got experience in it now
so I'm now like I've been here before I
know this works let's try this again
yeah
um so it's things like that but it's
quite interesting like talking about
mental health in general I think like I
said because it affects everyone yeah
like I mean look some people mix reviews
about uh opinions on it like I've heard
if you've got depression have a cup of
coffee and it'll go it doesn't quite
work like that I mean that's uh I'm not
saying all Builders are like that but
that was quite build a mentality yeah
but they're not all like that but um
yeah that was painful to listen to but
look I think that's just a lack of
slight education and I think that you
know they would have experienced people
who say stuff like that at some level of
sort of feeling a bit low and everything
like anyone would yeah because we are
humans we are emotional yeah we're
actual emotions sometimes yeah yeah
um and people ask start you can see the
trend going to where people ask starting
to be a bit more open about it but
there's there's definitely still some
sort of expectation of this like typical
British like stiff upper lip like yeah
head down with it like but the thing is
though like when something new comes
around like anything new so when the
fitness industry come out it's booming
okay but it's also going to be very
polarized because it's new you can have
all sorts of opinions okay so when we
talk about mental health some people
can take advantage of that so like I
think
um in the courses alone like you know
what is the actual diagnosis something
you had to fit a certain amount of
symptoms
um for you to be like well you'd
probably be here some people just have
like one and they're saying why I'm the
worst case thing and that's why it's
this handy Heaven professionals and
people you can talk to the guidelines to
work with as well but you can be a bit
more fluid with it because it is mental
health is a bit more fluid than like a
physical sort of thing yeah it's not
like one day you wake up and you've got
a cold you don't suddenly wake up and
there's like you're clinically diagnosed
with anxiety depression whatever it may
be like it is a sliding scale and things
do slip and slowly become better or
worse if you leave it unchecked I think
that's you know when you when you said
about you wake up and then you got this
XYZ and because someone just told you
like that's quite prominent in today's
society I've noticed yeah I think um
but you know like ADHD as an example or
like dyslexia or something like one of
my best mates because he spelled a word
wrong he's like well dyslexic then I was
like well I just self-diagnosed it's
self-diagnosed well I can put these
beans for a bit of string quick enough
so now I've got dyslexia like how does
that work mate yeah I mean he's a
plonker sometimes I love him I love him
but he's a bit of a lemon but you have a
lot more people now being like that
they're just throwing it around and I
think you have to be careful of that
yeah like you would in like set of
things like some people have arguments
you have to be careful what you say
because you know sometimes people say
some really silly things yeah so yeah I
think because we live in such a there's
never been so much information
accessible to communication yeah any
given point you just gotta pull this
computer or your phone out of your
pocket and you've got the answers to any
question you could ever want and all the
answers that you don't want to know as
well and so I think critical thinking
has become more important than ever
absolutely yeah you've got to understand
like whatever you're taking in you're
reading you've got to really look into
where is the source like what is it
where is the same information coming
from what is there any kind of like bias
one way or another and like you were
saying earlier it's important to have
Devil's Advocate and hear both sides of
the coin as well so I always look at the
word balance and balance is so important
and the problem is what I've seen is
people get told something and
immediately they're like I'm this I'm
that and now I'm not going to do
anything about it and we're almost
leaving the critical thinking and the
actual physical actions of things you
can take in place we use Fitness as an
example
you know I've heard some people say well
I've got this and that and there's no
point me getting to the gym yeah that's
quite it's quite a regressive way of
looking at it like you should go to the
gym because you can achieve these things
and that will put you in a better
position yeah oh but they said oh I
shouldn't because that I know you don't
know until you find out and I think a
lot of people are sort of I'm not saying
lazy because I don't think that's the
right thing to say but a lot of people
are getting very overwhelmed and then
it's quite a defeatist mindset and says
I'm not doing it then I've been like
that as well and lots of many other
people I know have been you have little
spats like that but it's becoming a bit
more prominent in today because there's
so many different things that you can
labels you can give yourself labels you
can be associated with so it gets quite
complex and so there doesn't need to be
a certain level structure I understand
everything is fluid and I and I'm
totally for it but that has have
structure with it as well otherwise it
could be almost anything yeah yeah
exactly I mean again that's a great
debate isn't it yeah I mean how
everyone's gonna be putting me in a box
yeah Jordan Peterson
you have similar things happen like I
noticed it really early on when I got
qualified as a PT you everyone just has
that assumption like when you're out of
the gym floor and you go to like family
events whatever you're like oh here's
Harry he's a PT and everyone's suddenly
ready to be like so what do I need to do
for my training what do you do yeah I
know just because I do this thing this
is not me as a person this is not 100 of
my identity and marching spoke about it
earlier he he used a phrase I haven't
heard before which was a commodification
of identity where you take one aspect of
something you do so let's say like you
play football you don't suddenly become
like I am football everything I do is
appeared around football and don't get
me wrong I'm saying this a son who's got
a basketball there there there's any
part of me but it's not it's not my sole
identity if I could suddenly if I'd
never played basketball again I wouldn't
lose a sense of who I was because I'm
not tied to one thing I mean to play
like Devil's Advocate and I think some
people in the world are just like that
and I'm sure we all met people like that
some people are only engross let's use
Fitness this example again obviously
because that's what we do but there's
some people are only married to the game
that I would only go to the gym I just
want to train I want to be myself I and
you know what that's totally fine
because you're entitled to do whatever
you want but I think there's a lot of
people there is um there's a bit more
depth to themselves like you know people
never guess like I could play piano like
I do not look like the person who can
play piano I look like all I do is just
do a bit of Raving of that
um but it's a little bit more to me yeah
but then when you say my background I
was raised by my grandma for like a few
years you know that kind of would make
sense but you know there's other things
and like so there is more depth to it
and yeah I know exactly what you mean
when you meet someone and they say oh
that's your job and then they just ask
you a lot of questions
and like because you're doing it all the
time you're like I want to stay away
from this yeah just because I will help
you but not right now what right now I
want I want what's my down time yeah
yeah I mean it's like they always think
you don't drink and stuff I don't drink
often but I definitely will have a pint
now and then yeah I down in the pub with
the boys at night I'll be watching the
footy watching my team win so
um of course you have a beer and things
like that I think they think you're all
quite like
um regimental I'm sure you get the same
thing if you bump into a client or
someone who recognizes from the gym yeah
like I'm a human just like you just
because I like help other people with
their exercise and nutrition the whole
point is to balance it so you can do
these things oh yeah I do and I love I
mean recently I went a night out and
sometimes you do but I bump into members
and that obviously that's just a thing
because you are here and so yeah you've
got to be careful and everything but um
and clients and that clients will prove
the worst ones because clients are like
they see you in in an element in in this
environment where you're like you're not
only your fan but you're have a serious
Point too and that's what they know so
then if they see you like with two
Corner bugs they're like you know what's
going on there you know but um I always
are liking it a little bit like you know
when you're at school and you just
assume the teachers live in the school
I know I feel like some people see pts
as people are just living in the gym and
that is their entire life and there's
nothing more to it there's more to us
guys there is there is more to us yeah
yeah it can be consuming especially when
you are self-employed because it's hard
to switch off when you're constantly
thinking about 20 things you can do but
sometimes not saying myself but I'm
saying there'll be other pts that are so
strict on it when they're outside of the
gym they're like the most
like wild most they blow a completely
way out the other way don't they yeah
I'm not saying we're the same as these
people but it's like the um the New York
Brokers have a severe cocaine addiction
yeah yeah they made us people who are
the sh on the outside looking at the
people who seem to be the most strict
disciplined like on the button every
single impulsiveness I can just switch
yeah yeah I've known a few of my friends
to have like one guy I know he had a
thousand day streak on my fitness pal
and then one that one day he broke it
and he went he was easily over like 8
000 calories ah mental if you're just
like maybe just rain it in a bit give
yourself like a little bit of time off
plan every now and again it'd be way
better than like yeah that's why we have
really strict all the time and maybe
it's having a complete blowout that's
why like when you train like you had
d-load weeks yeah yeah exactly and you
have times where you can be a bit more
fluctuating with your calories and
things like that again it goes back to
the word balance yeah like it always
does so people need to
kind of think about that and when you
think about balance and your pressures
aren't as high and if you have high
pressures with things where you put a
lot of pressure on yourself
it only invites
slight chaos which then can make rash
decisions and self you know negative
thinking yeah so when you look at like
that it's not different yeah yeah allow
yourself to have a night off every hour
and again oh yeah I mean that's what
sometimes Friday nights on Saturday
nights are for me you know yeah I'm all
I'm all for it you know so
um yeah it's funny when people look at
you when you see them a night out in the
pub or something they're like you don't
belong here yeah you don't belong here
yeah but um just gotta be careful so
with all of that but no
thanks for tuning in to find out more
from us hit the links in our description
for social medias or head to the website
which is integrityfitness.education
[Music]